<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A skirmish made upon Quakerism being a brief confutation of a most gross principle or point of doctrine published and maintained by one William Penn, a Quaker, in a certain book entituled Quakerism a nick-name for old Christianity, subverting religion and all duty both to God and man / by J.C.</title>
            <author>J. C. (John Cheyney)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08606288</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08606288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1250:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A skirmish made upon Quakerism being a brief confutation of a most gross principle or point of doctrine published and maintained by one William Penn, a Quaker, in a certain book entituled Quakerism a nick-name for old Christianity, subverting religion and all duty both to God and man / by J.C.</title>
                  <author>J. C. (John Cheyney)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Butler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to John Cheyney.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718. --  Quakerism a new nick-name for old Christianity.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41448:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SKIRMISH MADE UPON QUAKERISM: Being a Brief CONFUTATION OF A moſt groſs PRINCIPLE or Point of Doctrine:</p>
            <p>Publiſhed and Maintained by one <hi>WILLIAM PENN,</hi> a Quaker;</p>
            <p>In a certain Book, Entituled, <hi>Quakeriſm a Nick-name for old Chriſtianity,</hi> Subverting Religion, and all Duty both to God and Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> J. C. <hi>a Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Butler,</hi> next door to the <hi>Lamb</hi> and <hi>Three Bouls</hi> in <hi>Barbican.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:41448:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <p>Hic Tractatus, cui Titulus, <hi>A Skirmiſh upon Quakeriſme,</hi> &amp; cui nulla praefigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Praefatio.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Ab. Campion,</hi> Reverendiſſimo Domino Archiepiſc. <hi>Cant.</hi> à Sac. Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>16 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1676.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41448:2"/>
            <head>A SKIRMISH MADE UPON QUAKERISM.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here have riſen up in theſe dayes of outs a Sect of People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> about the Year, 1652. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring themſelves to be <hi>a People fearing God above all the Families of the Earth, and that do Worſhip him in his own Way,</hi> viz. <hi>in Spirit and in Truth; ſuch alſo as do love God above all, and their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as themſelves, &amp;c.</hi> (as we are told by their own Writers, <hi>Moderate Enquirer, Pag.</hi> 3.) concerning whom and their Principles many are ſufficiently informed by their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and Obſervation, and by the Writings which are extant; and are ſufficiently eſtabliſhed in the Truth by the Grace of God in their Souls, and are better able to over-throw erroneous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples than I. Confeſſing my own ſlender Abilities to any ſuch Service, and relying only upon the clearneſs of the Cauſe, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to tender to Chriſtian People an Account of one Capital Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and Fundamental Errour of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> aſſerted by one <hi>William Penn,</hi> who ſtyles himſelf one of them, in a Book Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Quakeriſm a new nick-Name for old Chriſtianity, Chap.</hi> 7. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71. with a brief confutation of it. If any one demand a reaſon of my doings in this caſe, I beg his candour and charity, reaſon of I have in mine own breaſt, known and approved to others that know me, I do not forbear to mention them, becauſe I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt them, but I think the matter needs not, and I would not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41448:3"/>trouble the Reader with more than needs; if God and Conſcience approve me, thou may'ſt well reſt in the matter delivered as ſome reaſon to ſtay thy enquiry, and a little charity will ſerve for the reſt, I have by me ſundry other of their Errours gathered out of their Books, very groſs and intolerable, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitation of them: but I forbear at preſent to make them publick; and ſhall only now preſent the Reader with one, but ſuch a one as may ſerve for all, and there needs no more to the ſubverting of all Piety, Charity and Equity then this one, which I here ſet down in his own Words: — <hi>No command in the Scripture is any farther obliging upon any Man, than as he finds a conviction upon his Conſcience. — It is conviction that can only oblige to Obedience. — When any Man is convinced, that what was commanded ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is required of him, then, and not till then he is rightly autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to perform it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the confutation of this Poſition, I ſhall advertiſe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe this, That the <hi>Quakers</hi> are by us charged to deny and ſubvert the Scriptures; which Charge they do deny, and account it a moſt vile and ungodly ſlander, and would not in any wiſe be thought to diminiſh ought in the leaſt from the juſt authority and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of the Scriptures, and profeſs to be great honourers of them, and to build their Religion and Hopes upon the Scriptures. So that by their own confeſſions they give us ground to argue from the Scriptures againſt them. I ſhall here manifeſt that for all their pretence and profeſſion of juſt reſpect to the Scriptures, they do quite ſubvert and undermine them, contradicting their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, and opening a Flood-gate to all Errour, Atheiſm, Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Wickedneſs; and that this Poſition of <hi>Penn's</hi> is the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of all Law and Government, a moſt intolerable and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Errour.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Since they profeſs ſo ſtick to the Scriptures, and that the Scriptures do in all Points make for them and againſt us, let them produce any one Text of Scripture, containing any ſuch aſſertion, or favouring it. Let <hi>Penn.</hi> produce any one Scripture, which willeth any Man to forbear Obedience to the command of God and Scripture, till he ſhall be convinced thereof, or ſuſpending the Authority and Obligation of Scripture-command till Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall be convinced. Let the whole Bible be conſulted, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41448:3"/>view every Command, and ſee if any ſuch clauſe can be found. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in all the ten Commandments where doth God ſay, none of theſe Commands ſhall oblige any Man whoſe Conſcience is uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, or contrary convinced. Inſtance in any the Precepts of the Goſpel, <hi>believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, repent and be converted, deny your ſelves and take up the Croſs, worſhip God in Spirit and in truth,</hi> and the like; where is there any ſuch clauſe as <hi>Penn</hi>'s; None of all theſe Commands ſhall oblige you further then you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced in Conſcience? So when the Scripture forbiddeth Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, forbiddeth Senſuality, or other ſin. Where doth it ſay, as <hi>Penn</hi> ſaith, None of theſe Prohibitions are obliging fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then there is a conviction upon your conſciences? I provoke him and all his partakers to produce any Word of Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Man's conviction as a condition antecedent to the being and binding force of God's commands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If this Poſition of <hi>Penn</hi>'s be true, then ſins of Ignorance are no ſins; for all conviction is by knowledge: where there is no knowledge, there can be no conviction upon the conſcience. So that this Poſition juſtifieth all ſins of Ignorance. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God in Scripture faith, <hi>It is a people of no underſtanding, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that made them will have no mercy on them,</hi> Iſa. 27.11. by <hi>Penn</hi>'s Poſition, it ſhould rather be ſaid, You want knowledge, and ſo want conviction, and therefore God will have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. And whereas God by Scripture ſaith, <hi>My people periſh for lack of knowledge,</hi> Hoſ. 4.6. by <hi>Penn</hi>'s Poſition it ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſaid, Your want of knowledge diſobligeth you from obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods commands, becauſe without knowledge you cannot be convinced, and without conviction the command of Scripture hath nothing to do with you. This doth juſtifie the <hi>Jews</hi> murder of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>they did it ignorantly,</hi> Acts 3.17. <hi>and had they known it they would not have crucified the Lord of glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.8. This doth juſtifie <hi>Paul</hi>'s Blaſphemy, and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and groſs ſins againſt the Goſpel, before his converſion, becauſe he ſaith, <hi>be did it ignorantly,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.13. And whereas <hi>Paul</hi> doth up and down confeſs his ſins, and acknowledgeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not worthy to be called an Apoſtle, becauſe he perſecuted the Church of God; <hi>Penn</hi>'s Poſition tells another ſtory, <hi>What needſt thou accuſe and judge thy ſelf before all the Churches of Chriſt by ſuch
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41448:4"/>confeſſions, for no command in Scripture is of any ſuch force to oblige ignorant unbelieving ſinners: Thou didſt all this in thy ignorance and unbelief, and therefore they were no ſins and crimes, and if no crimes, they were innocent, yea laudable actions proceeding from a mind acting according to conviction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If this Poſition of <hi>Penn</hi>'s be true, then ſins of errour are no ſins, but vertues; and whatſoever is done through deluſion, and a perverted hereticated mind and judgment is laudable. <hi>I verily thought</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that I ought to do many things contrary to the name of Jeſus Chriſt of Nazareth,</hi> Acts 26.9. and our Saviour ſaith, <hi>The time cometh, that whoſoever killeth you, will think that he doth God ſervice,</hi> Joh. 16.2. <hi>It it conviction</hi> (ſaith <hi>Penn</hi>) <hi>which can only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige to obedience:</hi> doth not this patronize the groſſeſt crimes, where the conſcience is miſconvinced and the underſtanding decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? doth not this juſtifie all erroneous Doctrines? and all erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Conceits, and practical Miſapprehenſions, and whatſoever Vices lye in the underſtandings of Men? for all conviction paſſeth into the Soul through this gate of the underſtanding. Now the underſtanding is naturally full of darkneſs, unbelief, and errour; every ungodly man is practically an Atheiſt, an Heretick, a falſe Teacher to his own ſoul at leaſt, and practical Ignorance and a perverted Judgement, are the mother of all the ſins and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the world: and what doth this Poſition but juſtifie them all? When wicked men kill the Saints, they look upon them at wicked men, and ſo kill them; all that have been martyr'd by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Popes, and Pagan Kings and Governours, and all the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions that have been done to the Saints, have been through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and practical errour. <hi>Penn</hi>'s Poſition doth juſtifie the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, the <hi>French</hi> Maſſacre, the <hi>Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Perſection, the ten Perſecutions of the Primitive Churches, the Gun-powder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Judaiſm, Mahometiſm, Paganiſm, Popery, all erroneous Sects and Parties in the World, with all their falſe Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>it is life eternal to know God and Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Joh. 17.3. <hi>Penn</hi>'s Poſition ſaith, <hi>if you are ignorant and unconvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, no Law can lay hold on you; if you be deluded, and practiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the convictions of your deluded mind, you are warranted by the command of God, which do all center in conviction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. If this Poſition off <hi>Penn</hi>'s be true, then conſcience and convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41448:4"/>is God, and whatſoever conſcience ſays muſt be done, be it right or wrong, and it lyes in the power of conſcience to abrogate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do and make void all the Laws of God, and to make new Laws in their room and ſtead, and do whatſoever it pleaſeth. If no command be of any force further then conſcience ſhall aſſent to it, and if conviction, and conviction only oblige to obedience, then whatſoever conviction ſays muſt be done, let God and Man ſay what tehy will. If conviction bid us murder, we muſt do it, if to commit Treaſon we muſt do it, and that under pain of damnation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Then alſo it will follow, that he is the moſt free from all ſin who hath the moſt ſear'd conſcience, and that the ready way to obedience and ſalvation is to debauch and ſear the conſcience, and and ſtuff it with the groſſeſt errours, and quite kill it with conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-waſting ſins, and make it ſo void of life and feeling, that we may may do the moſt horrid crimes, and yet conſcience ſtand to ſtand to them, and not only not ſmite us for them, but approve us, and praiſe us, and tell us we have done God good ſervice.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If conviction be the ground of obedience, and the authority of Scripture depend upon the rectitude and purity of conſcience, then all rational Law, Order and Government both Divine and Humane is over turned, and a ſtop is put to all Religion and Piety towards God, to all Conſcience, Honeſty and Charity towards Men, let God command what he will, conſcience may come and ſay, I deny this command, and him that commands it. I know no ſuch God, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſayes to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Who is the Lord that I ſhould let Iſrael go? I know not the Lord, neither will I let Iſrael go,</hi> Exod. 5.2. and as proud <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſayes to the three Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>who is that God that ſhall deliver you out of my hand?</hi> Dan. 3.15. and as <hi>Sennacherib</hi> ſent a railing Letter by his Captain <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> blaſpheming the God of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Who is your God, that be ſhould be able to deliver you out of my hand?</hi> 2 Chron. 32.14. <hi>No God of any Nation or Kingdom was able to deliver out of my hand, how much leſs ſhall your God deliver you out of my hand?</hi> v. 15. <hi>And his ſervants ſpake yet more againſt the Lord God, and his ſervant</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah; <hi>he wrote Letters alſo to rail on the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and to ſpeak againſt him, &amp;c.</hi> v. 16, 17. So alſo Princes and Rulers may command and make never ſo good Laws, conſcience may come and ſay, I deny all theſe Laws, and the maker of them: Children
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41448:5"/>may refuſe to obey Parents, and Servants their Maſters, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours their Superiours, if conſcience ſhall be unconvinced, and if it be deluded, Subjects may murder their Princes, Children their Parents, Servants their Maſters, one Man another, there can be no Law but Conſcience, and whatſoever Conſcience ſays muſt ſtand.</p>
            <p>It is certain, that ſince the fall of our firſt Parents Conſcience in every man naturally is corrupted, and by cuſtom in ſin it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>comes twice corrupted. By nature Conſcience is <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and ſins,</hi> Eph. 2.1. and men <hi>live without God and Chriſt in the world,</hi> v. 12. being <hi>without hope, and aliens to the Common-wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers to the Covenants of Promiſe:</hi> By nature there is not one righteous conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence in all the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10. <hi>There is none that underſtandeth, there is none that ſeeketh after God, they are all gone out of the way, they altogether become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one,</hi> v. 11.12. All the world is guilty before God of an evil conſcience, <hi>v.</hi> 19. The mind and conſcience is defiled, <hi>abominable, diſobedient, and to every good work reprobate,</hi> Tit. 1.15, 16. Some mens conſciences are twice dead, <hi>Jud.</hi> 12. <hi>ſeared with a hot iron,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 2. <hi>paſt feeling, given over to laſciviouſneſs, to work all uncleanneſs with greedineſs,</hi> Eph. 4.19. <hi>hard as the ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant ſtone,</hi> Zach. 7.12. <hi>having a whores forehead, without ſhame,</hi> Jer. 3.3. <hi>impudent and ſtiff-hearted,</hi> Ezek. 2.4. <hi>rebellious,</hi> v. 5. <hi>doing evil with both hands earneſtly, Mich. 7.3. inſatiable,</hi> Ezek. 16.28. <hi>full of ſubtilty and miſchief, children of the Devil, enemies of all righteouſneſs, not ceaſing to pervert the right ways of the Lord,</hi> Act. 13.10. and infinite more might be gathered out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, reporting the wickedneſs of man, and the corruptions of his Conſcience, and all his powers.</p>
            <p>Experience witneſſeth the ſame, what woful conſciences have many profeſſing Chriſtians? <hi>Penn</hi> himſelf ſaith of the Proteſtants, and them of the Church of <hi>England, That they abound in evil, equalizing, if not outſtripping Papiſts and Heathens in all kinds of impiety, Truth exalted, p.</hi> 10. how then can ſuch a conſcience be a law or rule to all the world, and ſuſpend and make void the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of all Gods Laws? the Quakers conſcience ſays one thing, the Papiſts conſcience ſays another thing, the Pagans conſcience, the Turks conſcience, Jews conſcience, the Tyrants conſcience, the Traitors conſcience, the Hereticks conſcience, the Worldlings
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41448:5"/>conſcience, the Hypocrites conſcience, the proud mans, conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Adulterers conſcience. How many contrary Conſcience are theſe? how many Gods ſhall we have, and how many contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory Laws, if Conſcience and Conviction be the only thing which obligeth to duty, and no Law or Command of Scripture oblige, Conſcience repugning and being unconvinced?</p>
            <p>I would know of <hi>Penn</hi> or any man elſe, what conviction there is upon a Drunkards conſcience when he is dead drunk in his drunkenneſs, and yet <hi>Penn</hi>'s. Poſition is, that no Command in Scripture is obliging upon the Drunkard to repent and be ſober, ſuppoſing him in his drunkenneſs unconvinced. The moſt godly Miniſters find by ſad experience, it is one of the hardeſt matters in the world to convince an impenitent man of his impenitency, to convince a worldling of his worldlineſs, to convince a ſinner of heart-ſins, ſuch as heart-pride, heart-malignity againſt God and godlineſs, heart unbelief, and Atheiſm, and irreligion, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and earthlineſs, and other luſts and, vices. And if <hi>Penn</hi> and his fellows ſhall lay the blame upon the Preacher, and ſay the fault is in Preachers, and not in People, let him take heed leſt he charge God and Chriſt, and the Holy Ghoſt and Scripture, and Prophets and Apoſtles, who have preached to ſinners as well as we, and yet thouſands have remained unconvinced. Will <hi>Penn</hi> undertake to anſwer for all the crimes of an ignorant, blind, and erroneous conſcience againſt the commands in Scipture? Will he be an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate at the day of Judgment to plead the cauſe of unconvinced conſciences, and maintain his Poſition then to the face of God, as now he doth publiſh it to the world, and pretend to write from the warrant of God, and from the ſenſe of his eternal ſpirit, <hi>Reaſon againſt Railing, p.</hi> 164. and crying down the obſervation of the Lords Supper, and Baptiſm, as ſottiſh, and that a ſpirit of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from God, groſs Apoſtacy into Superſtition and Idolatry, yea a ſpirit of Hypocriſie, Perſecution and Murder, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wickedneſs hath got them, and covered it ſelf with them. <hi>p.</hi> 108, 109. And he teſtifies from the ſame ſpirit, that <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Circumciſion, that the Appellation, Ordinances of Chriſt, and particularly Baptiſm and the Lords Supper are to be rejected.</p>
            <p>Had this Poſition been, that every command in Scripture is not obliging upon every man, it had been ſound Doctrine, for we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41448:6"/>acknowledge, that every command of God is not obliging to every man, but only ſuch commands as it is Geds will and intent that they ſhould be obliging to all. Some commands of God are but temporary, perſonal and local. Many commands in Scripture are long ſince abrogated and null. The command to <hi>Abrabam</hi> to ſlay his Son, was extraordinary, and not to be obeyed by any without the like warrant. The command to ſacrifice ſlain Beaſt, to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe, the command of the Paſsover, theſe are ceaſed. We may ſufficiently collect Gods mind from his word, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are temporary, and extraordinary, and concern but ſome particular men, and do only oblige in certain caſes, and which be perpetual, and oblige all men, at all times, in all places, and the love of God and Man, innocency, holineſs, godlineſs, faith, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, truth, temperance, ſelf-denyal, zeal for Gods glory, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that Parents bring up Children in Gods fear, that Children honour their Parents, that we do to all men as we would be done unto, and a multitude more ſuch like. Now <hi>Penn</hi>'s Poſition is, That no command at all in Scripture is obliging without convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the conſcience; and he makes conviction to be the only thing obliging and authorizing to duty, and to be of ſuch force, that without conviction no command at all bindeth. For if that be the reaſon why Gods command written obligeth not, becauſe the conſcience in not convinced, then <hi>ubi eadem ratio ibi eadem lex,</hi> an unwritten command of God obligeth not where there is no conviction. And ſince all Gods Laws are comprized within theſe two of written and unwritten, Precepts written in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Precepts unwritten and contained in Nature, it will follow, that no Law of God is further obliging any man than he is convinced of it, that it is Gods Law, and that he ſtands bound to obey it. It will then follow, That if the Conſcience be blind, erroneous, ſeared, and corrupt, there muſt needs be a multitude of things in Gods Laws moſt weighty and important duties, which the conſcience will be utterly ignorant of, and will call good evil, and evil good, and juſtifie that which God doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, and condemn what God doth juſtifie, and will walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God, againſt which is the woe in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.30.</p>
            <p>For it is certain, that a carnal man diſcerneth not ſpiritual things, and all Gods commands are ſpritual; every command of God is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41448:6"/>holy and pure and ſpiritual, whether it be written in Scripture or written in Nature, and without a ſpiritual Principle in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the conſcience being carnal and blind, diſcerneth not ſpiritual things; and ſo it will follow that all ſpiritual obedience to Gods Laws is made void.</p>
            <p>Can <hi>Penn</hi> anſwer this or confute it? let him. Let him demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate how a carnal conſcience can obey a ſpirtual command, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man by nature is earthly, Gods commands are heavenly, we are by nature unholy, Gods Laws are holy. If Gods Laws bind none but ſuch as be convinced of them, and no further then they are convinced, then it will unanſwerably follow, that no man in the World is under any Law of God to perform ſpiritual obedience. For inſtance, Gods command is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not murder.</hi> Now this command is a ſpiritual command, requiring the ſubjection of the heart, and condemning all Murder both of Soul and Body, and whatſoever is a degree of it, and tendeth to it. Now no unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate carnal conſcience doth diſcern this command of God in its extent and ſpirituality, he is no convinced of it, and by <hi>Penn</hi>'s Poſition there lies upon him no obligation to ſpirutal obedience.</p>
            <p>Had it not behoved <hi>Penn</hi> to make good his Poſition by ſolid proof? it had, eſpecially when called to it by <hi>John Faldo,</hi> who chargeth the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and that juſtly, for ſubverting the Scriptures. What ſayes <hi>Penn</hi> for proof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> why he contradicts himſelf, or ſayes ſomething like a contradiction, which is frequent in his Writings.</p>
            <p>Firſt he ſayes, <hi>that no command of Scripture is obliging upon any man further then he hath a conviction upon his conſcience;</hi> afterwards he ſayes, <hi>that ſuch commands as theſe, be holy, be juſt, be ſober,</hi> and ſuch like, together with holy Examples are obliging upon all; Why? becauſe they more or leſs meet with a conviction in the conſciences of all: <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I am perſwaded, none that has a reaſonable ſoul, who has not out-lived their dayes, and on whom the night is not come, among the</hi> Indians <hi>themſelves, but would readily ſay, theſe are true and weighty.</hi> And ſo he wipes himſelf and his Brother <hi>Burroughs</hi> as he thinks clean, and acquits himſelf from all crime againſt the Scriptures, and evades <hi>John Faldo</hi>'s Charge. But not to ſtand anſwering every word, the ſum of <hi>Penn</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and come off (to give it the Reader in more intelligible words) is this: <hi>That ſuch commands in Scripture as be of univerſal
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41448:7"/>and perpetual obligation, ſuch as holineſs, purity, innocency and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all that concerns honeſt and godly living, all theſe be obliging to all, becauſe there is no man ſo ſottiſh and impious but his conſcience aſſenteth to theſe commands:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> what do you ſay, if men be ſo ſottiſh and impious as to be ignorant that theſe are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, and to live without God in the World, and to have abominable and filthy and reprobate conſciences? It is plain from your Poſition and defence of it, that you make conviction the ground and ſpring of obedience. So that where there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, there is no obedience due; where the conviction is but partial, the obedience due is but partial; where the conviction is erroneous, the obedience muſt be erroneous. It this Divinity? and is this your Religion? Why then do you not ſpeak out and ſay, fully and plainly, Every man follow his own Luſts, every man follow his own conſcience, every man burn his Bible, and make Conſcience and Conviction your Bible? For this is the genuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of your Opinion. It is a Rule in Logick, That what is not in the premiſes cannot be in the concluſion, and that every redundancy in the concluſion exceeding the Arguments laid down in the premiſes in vicious, and that the concluſion is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually contained in the two fore-going Propoſitions. Now you make conviction one of your premiſes, and you lay down this Propoſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That where there is no conviction, there is no obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that obedience can riſe no higher than conviction.</p>
            <p>Now may one not admire, that a man of your reading and bringing up ſhould be ſo perſwaded of the holineſs and goodneſs of Man-kind, as to write and publiſh to the World, <hi>That none that hath a reaſonable ſoul, no not among the</hi> Indians <hi>themſelves, can be unconvinced of that faith in God, and an holy ſelf-denying life are neceſſary both to temporal and eternal happineſs.</hi> — <hi>Quis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alia fando temperet à lachrymis?</hi> The Lord forgive me my want of compaſſion to this man. Alas, how many thouſands are there in the World that know not God, not what faith in God is, that know not what a holy ſelf-denying life is, that worſhip Devils, that make the Belly their God, and with them a holy ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life is to live as if the muſt never dye, and follow their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and Religion with them is meer Epicuriſm and ſenſuality, let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhall dye.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41448:7"/>
            <p>You would have us to believe, that all the World is perfectly holy, and that there is never a corrupted and defiled conſcience in the World, and that <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall is no ſuch thing, and that the redemption of Man-kind by Chriſts blood, and regeneration by the Holy Ghoſt, and original ſin, and hereditary corruption, and mans deadneſs in ſins and treſpaſſes by nature, are no ſuch things. O marvellous! that you can be perſwaded, no man that hath a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoul, not a ſavage <hi>Indian,</hi> but he hath a conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him aſſenting to all the rules and precepts of holineſs, ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal, godlineſs, charity, and heavenly converſation: or that no man in the World hath a blind underſtanding, a ſeared conſcience, an impotent foul, needing no purgation and cure from Jeſus Chriſt, and his good ſpirit by the new covenant.</p>
            <p>I do grant you this, that no man ſtands bound to obey any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand which it is utterly impoſſible for him to know and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of. And by granting this, I do ſufficiently aſſoil and clear the juſtice of God. God doth not enjoyn any man that which is ſimply and totally impoſſible. God and Conſcience will never ſmite and condemn for meer and total impoſſibilities. But where nothing hinders a man from knowing his duty but his own neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and wilful careleſneſs; and where a man ſhall by ſin debauch and ſear his Conſcience, and Conſcience miſguided and ſeduced ſhall put him on to worſhip Idols, to bow to a wooden God, to blaſpheme the true God, to murder, perſecute, commit all or any crimes; will you excuſe this man from ſin for going according to his Conſcience, and exempt him from all, going againſt his erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Conſcience?</p>
            <p>If indeed the caſe were ſo that no conviction could be, or none that I could any way compaſs, then I were in no fault: but where it is my fault, if I be unconvinced, and I might know my duty were I not wanting to my ſelf, and there is no defect in the means, but all the defect is in me, in ſuch caſe God may juſtly charge me with the omiſſion of duty, and the commiſſion of evil though I know not of it: for I might have known if I would; and my not knowing my duty which I might have known, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not excuſe me from ſin, nor nullify the command of God. If God ſhould command a Beaſt to do him reaſonable worſhip, it were an unreaſonable command, becauſe the beaſt hath no reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41448:8"/>powers or capacity thereto, the command to him is ſimply im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. So if God ſhould command a man to reach the Stars with his hands, ſuch a command would not oblige, becauſe it is naturally and ſimply impoſſible. But when God commandeth the <hi>Jews</hi> to believe on the ſame Jeſus, and own him for the true Meſſias, this command is reaſonable, becauſe Jeſus Chriſt doth abundantly teſtifie by his doctrine, life, and miracles, that he is the Chriſt of God. And if the <hi>Jews</hi> will not believe, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe look upon Chriſt as a deliverer, and put him to death, and all this in blind zeal, and think they do God good ſervice, ſhall we ſay, Theſe men are excuſed, becauſe they did it ignorantly and of errour? In all caſes where God doth afford due means of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conviction, there ignorance and baſe want of convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſinful, and Gods command both written and unwritten doth oblige, though the ſinner be never convinced. For mans ſin and neglect cannot make void Gods Law. It is true, I grant that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the light within we could not at all come to the knowledge of the Scriptures. What then? will it thence follow, That no command in Scripture doth oblige without conviction? Had we no light within we ſhould be very brutes. Every man hath a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſoul, which ſoul doth eſſentially contain a principle or power of rational light, by which man, as man is differenced from a beaſt, and is <hi>Animal rationale,</hi> by the help of his reaſon, or that light which is graven in his mind by the Creatour, and cultivated by education, he may know that there is a God and a Life to come, and many things pertaining to Religion and Morality<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Will it hence follow, that becauſe we are men and have reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able faculties, there lyes no obligation upon us, to obey any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, further then our reaſon ſhall acquaint and certifie us, and further then the light ſhall inform us? What if the light be negligent, idle, ſleepy, unfaithful, and bribed, and ſhall let the ſinner ſin, and dye in ſin, is God unjuſt for taking vengeance? If the Coach-man ſleep and the Horſes run wood, or if he drive ſo that the Coach is over-turned, doth he not deſerve correction? But <hi>Penn</hi> and all his partakers conceit ſtrange things of the light within, and ſet it above Scriptures, above all written and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Laws, and this is their very Principle, That the light within in all things is to be, our Rule, and that the Scripture is inferiour to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41448:8"/>it, and to be ruled by it, and ſo God and Chriſt, and the Spirit and Scripture and all Duty and Religion are made ſervants to the light within. Whereas it is evident, That the light within gives the Drunkard leave to be drunk, the Worldlng to be a worldling, and the impenitent man to be impenitent, there is never a ſoul in Hell but he may have the light within, for if the light within were faithful to God and the Soul, it would not ſuffer ſin to dwell in the ſoul, it would not ſuffer any man to live in ſin and dye in ſin. God charges man to be holy in all manner of converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and man being ſo charged by God doth quire the contrary. The light within which ſhould be his guide, like a negligent drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Coach-man ſleeps, and the Horſes run wood, or he drives in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to pits and bogs. So doth the light within take part with the fleſh, and Satan againſt God, and ſuffers the ſoul to be ſenſual, worldly, and ungodly, and ſo is at leaſt a permiſſive cauſe of the ſinners ſin and damnation; being charged to watch over the ſoul, and doth not. Now comes <hi>Penn</hi> and a Sect of people called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and cry, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p with this light within, and tell us, that we muſt hearken to this in all things; and further then the light within ſhall teach and lead us we are to give no hearkning to any thing that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith;</hi> and if Scripture go, farewell God and Chriſt, and Heaven, and all Law and Rule. This is that <hi>Penn</hi> whoſe zeal for <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſm</hi> exceeds, that hath written ſundry Books for it, and in the end of his Book, <hi>Reaſon againſt Railing, pag.</hi> 185. doth commend unto us his own with other his Brethrens Works, for an account of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Principles, confeſſing, That they do contain much of what can be ſaid in behalf of their Principles and Practices, vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as though they could not by reaſon be ſilenced, nor confuted by ſober Argument, <hi>pag.</hi> 186. I refer my ſelf and what I have here writ to impartial cenſure, warning and entreating all people, as they love their ſouls, to take heed of <hi>Quakeriſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would be glad to make the beſt I can of your Poſition, but I muſt proteſt my Conſcience and Conviction, I cannot find out what to ſay to ſolve your Poſition, and make it but a tolerable Errour. All this while I ſpeak not againſt you but your Errour; you make bold and free to publiſh ſuch matter to the World, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us the ſame boldneſs and freedom to detect your Errours, and to do our beſt to ſave the Souls which be in danger to be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41448:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubverted by your Principles. Keep your poyſon to your ſelf, and none will periſh by it but your ſelf: but if you will needs vend it, and in the view of all the Nation, and ſuch at leaſt as know the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongues ſet up a Poſition ſubverting all Religion, and all Law and Government, and levelling all holy and profitable Rules and Commands to mens luſts, leaving no man in the World un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any obligation to any duty to God or Man further then he is convinced in his conſcience, be it known to you, that Jeſus Chriſt hath his ſervants abroad to bear teſtimony for him againſt ſuch God-baſpheming and Soul-damning Errours, and if you repent not, this that I have writ ſhall riſe up in judgment againſt you, and ſhall be an aggravation of your miſery in that day.</p>
            <p>Prepare to anſwer the righteous Judge, if your Conſcience be blinded and ſeared now, it will be open and awaken then.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 6. 1676.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
